I once made a film with Laney Reefen,
the notorious German film director who
made propaganda films for the Nazis. And
she told me that Hitler told her that he
decided to join the Nazi party while
looking down on the world from a
mountain. Now, I don't know if that's
true, but I do know that mountains have
a powerful effect on people.
Mountains cloud your judgment.
They heighten your emotions and
intoxicate you.
And in Renaissance times, the times
we're looking at, they intoxicated that
especially disquing Renaissance
presence.
Leonardo da Vinci.
[music]
When Leonardo pops up in Renaissance
films, he's always presented as this
great gatherer of knowledge. Leonardo,
artist and scientist, the leading genius
of the Renaissance. And of course, he
was very clever and all that, but he was
also driven, unsettling,
imbalanced, [clears throat]
and that's the Leonardo we'll be looking
at in this film.
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Personally, I can't see how Leonardo
ever managed to pass for a scientific
genius. One look at his paintings tells
you there was something strange about
him, something peculiar and visionary.
So in this film, a film about the
darkness that enveloped the Renaissance
as it hurtled through the 16th century,
we'll be celebrating Leonardo the fiery
visionary
and not Leonardo the brilliant
scientist.
And then when we've done with Leonardo,
we'll turn to all the other wildeyed
eccentrics
who began popping up in the Renaissance
in increasing numbers.
Heronimous Bosch,
Arkim Baldo,
El Greco.
The Renaissance is supposed to be the
first modern age of reason,
but look how packed it really was with
unreason.
We have to start here, of course, with
the world's most famous painting.
[music]
Painted in around 1504,
the Mona Lisa has spent half a
millennium confusing people.
I must have seen her a hundred times and
I still can't tell you what that
mysterious look on her face is trying to
convey.
It's all deliberate. Leonardo, the
cunning soando, is playing mind games
with us. With most portraits, you look
at the sitter. With this one, the sitter
looks at you, staring slowly into your
thoughts as if she knows what you're
thinking.
That's why she's got that irritating
smirk on her face, the famous Mona Lisa
smile.
Damn it, she knows everything.
Apart from these psychological games
which are brilliant and way ahead of
their time, what I really admire about
her is that she's not classically
beautiful.
This isn't a renaissance dolly bird or a
standin for Venus.
This is a smart older woman, independent
and strong.
When you admire the Mona Lisa, you
admire her mystery,
not her cuteness.
And that's where the mountains come in.
These fabulous Leonardo mountains.
The landscape here is really important.
Usually in art, the landscape helps to
place the sitter so you know where you
are. But with the Mona Lisa,
the opposite happens.
Leonardo's mountains echo her sense of
mystery and amplify it.
Smuggled into Renaissance art timeless
moods
that belong in Lord of the Rings.
The same thing happens all over his art.
The pictures play mind games with you.
This is the Virgin of the Rocks also in
the Louve. And again, what a puzzling
picture with all this strange pointing
going on. And another stupendous and
thoroughly mysterious mountain landscape
like a clever who done it that we'll
never solve. The art of Leonardo da
Vinci keeps us guessing,
speculating,
and suspecting.
It's true of so much of his art, as if
he's deliberately stoking [snorts] up
the sense of mystery to keep us
interested.
And very often it involves mountains.
In Windsor Castle, in the Royal Library,
there's a remarkable set of drawings.
the socalled deluge drawings
made towards the end of his life
in around 1514.
And all of them have this turbulent
apocalyptic
power to them.
When I first saw these deluge pictures,
I assumed they were scientific drawings
in which Leonardo was recording the
effects of a particularly fierce storm.
And we now know that in 1513
there really was a terrible landslide
here in Bellenzona near the Swiss border
with Italy and that Leonardo may have
witnessed the damage as the mountain
crumbled and slid into the valley.
And guess what? Just recently in 2012,
it happened again in this same valley.
You can see it on YouTube. The Bellin
Zona landslide.
It's very dramatic.
So, this was something that actually
happened. It looks imaginary, but it
wasn't. It's the same with another
drawing in the Royal Library in Windsor
called the cloudburst of material
possessions in which all sorts of garden
implements are falling out of the sky.
Rakes, bottles, umbrellas.
You can see that on YouTube as well. A
few months ago, it happened near Venice
when a tornado struck the Vento
and all this stuff began falling out of
the sky.
So all this can really happen. Nature
can tear the world apart and reorder it.
It's scientifically observable and
provable. But there's something else
going on here. If you look at the top,
see, Leonardo's written something in his
famous mirror writing, and it actually
says, "On this side, Adam. On this Eve,
Adam and Eve, the first man and the
first woman in the Bible,
who committed the first sin."
What have they got to do with any of
this?
They've got everything to do with it.
Because what we've really got in these
tremendous deluge drawings is an intense
and pessimistic religious vision
disguised as science.
Here's another of the deluge drawings.
A hurricane sweeping across the sky,
uprooting the trees, drowning the
horsemen.
And look up in the clouds, hidden in the
billows, an angry god is driving the
storm.
Look over here in the corner. See,
there's a cloud load of trumpeting
angels blowing the final chord.
We've seen angels like this before in
this series.
Back in film two when we visited the
cyine chapel and saw Michelangelo's
last judgment
where another cloud load of trumpeting
angels
is playing the final tune.
These Delu's drawings may look like
accurate observations of nature, things
that Leonardo actually saw, but what
they really are are fantastical
envisionings of the final apocalypse,
the end of the world.
This isn't the handiwork of a
particularly clever scientist.
It's the handiwork of a particularly
pessimistic visionary.
In the mind of Leonardo da Vinci,
exquisite knowledge had turned into
[music]
exquisite despair.
>> [bell]
>> He sendeth the springs into the
[singing] rivers.
All beasts of the field drink thereof.
[singing]
>> Scratch the surface of the Renaissance
just about anywhere and the pessimism
comes bubbling up like Saudi crude.
It's true of many Renaissance hotspots,
[singing]
>> but it's especially true of this one.
>> When it comes to pessimism,
even Leonardo has some way to go to
match the despair of Heronimous Bosch.
[singing]
of men.
>> Bosch was almost an exact contemporary
of Leonardos, just a couple of years
older. He was born around 1450,
died 1516.
So this pessimism they shared was the
pessimism of their times.
[music]
As the 15th century turned into the
16th,
art, the truest evidence there is of
these things,
got weirder and weirder,
darker and darker.
This is supposed to be an age of
enlightenment.
So where did the enlightenment [music]
go?
Bosch was born over there in Stoen Bosch
or Denbos as they call it now in
Holland. He was christened Heronomous
Van Ahan. But just as Veronese came from
Verona and Dainci came from Vinci, so
Bosch came from Denbos.
His most famous picture, the garden of
earthly delight in the Prao.
That extraordinary theme park of sin
is a tptic packed with so much bad news
that I can't deal with it all at once.
So, I'm going to do the three panels
separately.
The one on the left shows us paradise
where God has just created Adam and Eve.
So there they all are standing under a
dragon tree.
And because this is paradise,
Satan is there as well, but he's in
disguise.
He's usually shown as a snake,
but Bosch reinvents him as an owl
lurking in his cubby hole at the center
of paradise.
The owl, the dragon tree, they're all
symbolic details and the picture is
jam-packed with them. It took us 3 hours
to film it in the Praau and we still
didn't finish.
Bosch was part of a large family of
painters, the Van Arans,
who worked communally in a house by the
market in Denbos.
With everyone chipping in,
they all lived and worked in a studio on
the square here. And that is where the
garden of earthly delight would have
been painted.
While the left hand panel [music] shows
us paradise,
the central panel is a picture of
Disneyland.
Oops. Sorry. No, it isn't. It's just
that it looks like it with its
Cinderella castles and its sleeping
beauty fountains
and all that romping and reveling in the
grass.
What it actually shows is paradise a bit
later on as it were once the humans and
the animals have settled in and spurred
on by Satan begin doing what humans and
animals always do when you let them off
the leash.
Show a man a woman and he'll sin with
her.
Show a woman a man and she'll tempt him.
Or so Bosch is telling us as he warns us
in excruciating and marvelous detail
of the unstoppable dangers of lust.
Because Bosch's art is so strange, some
very daft suggestions have been put
forward to explain it, particularly that
middle panel.
It's been claimed that he used
hallucinogenic drugs to imagine this
renaissance LSD perhaps.
and Freudians have outed him as a
repressed sedo masochist.
Another popular idea is that he was a
member of a secret religious cult and
that his art was smuggling wicked
heretical ideas into the Renaissance.
But of course, he wasn't any of those
things. Bosch was a fierce and inventive
Catholic, a religious pessimist who
looked around at the world about him and
didn't like what he saw. He sendeth the
springs into the river.
>> In Bosch's time, Sir Tegan Bosch had
about 18,000 people living in it. And of
those 18,000,
2,000 or so were religious folk,
>> monks, friars,
>> nuns,
[singing]
>> so this was an unusually religious town
>> and these unusually religious moods are
his moods. the cattle
and green up for the service [singing]
of men that he may bring food out of the
earth.
>> It's been suggested that a version of
the garden of earthly delights used to
hang here in the cathedral in Sir
Tugenbos,
but the nudity was too much for later
times,
>> so it was replaced. And the [singing]
wilderes
quench their thirst.
Some of the strange architecture in the
garden was inspired by this new font for
baptizing children which arrived in the
cathedral in 1492.
He
above
>> Bosch converted it into an ungodly blue
totem that the locals are worshiping in
their religious Disneyland.
[singing]
>> Full of guilt and terror, set free in
paradise,
mankind gets straight down to the
business of forgetting the true God.
The Lord shall [singing]
works.
>> So the central panel is packed with
sinners and all that sinning can only
lead to one place,
hell. And that's what's depicted in the
right hand panel.
[singing]
>> Hell is Bosch's specialtity.
He painted the most imaginative and
terrifying scenes of punishment and
distortion
>> to be found anywhere in art.
[singing]
>> I don't need to describe them.
>> You can see what they are.
>> The only thing that needs pointing out
perhaps is that this is Renaissance art
as well. Just as Renaissance as the Mona
Lisa,
[singing]
the darkness of Heronimous Bosch,
the sweaty guiltiness of his art,
all that punishment and sin. in isn't
confined to Renaissance painting.
It's a feature too of Renaissance
ceramics
and particularly of the remarkable
plates made in Renaissance France by
Bernard Palissi.
Palissi was a French hugeno, a
Protestant. He was born in around 1510
and died aged about 80 in the Bastile
prison. They locked him up because he
was fiercely religious and refused to
denounce his Protestant faith.
We're not sure where Palissi learned to
make his remarkable Renaissance plates.
He seems to have been largely
self-taught.
They say he was trying to recreate
Chinese porcelain,
but I don't think I buy that.
It's obvious surely that pali's plates
have a dark side.
A typical palisi will have a snake in
the middle and all around will be
lizards, snails, frogs, things that
slither and creep and come out of the
deep.
[music]
They're spectacularly realistic and
ahead of their times.
He made them using plaster molds taken
from real snakes and lizards he'd
collected in the marshes.
Why would anyone in Renaissance France
be making plates like these?
In art, snakes, lizards, frogs have a
very dark history. They've been
victimized,
picked out of the animal kingdom and
turned into symbols of death and evil.
When Carpacio painted his fabulous St.
George and the Dragon in the Squala San
Gio in Venice.
He littered the ground around his hero
with symbols of darkness, mutilation,
and mortality.
also in Venice. Why is this young man
painted by Lorenzo Lotto
being examined so intently by a lizard?
Because the lizard's job in the painting
is to remind the young man that youth is
short and death is waiting.
It all starts in the Bible, which is
packed with prejuditial views of
reptiles and amphibians.
When a plague descends on God's chosen
people in Exodus, it's a plague of
frogs.
And right at the start in Genesis, when
Satan tempts Eve in the Garden of Eden,
he does it disguised as a snake.
So these aren't any old religious
issues. These are the critical ones.
[music]
The only reason we have to die at all
according to the Bible is because we
sinned in paradise.
[music]
And why did we sin in paradise?
Because a snake tempted Eve to commit
the first sin.
And Bernard Palissi, a religious
extremist who died in the Bastile for
his beliefs,
would have known all about the terrible
meaning of snakes, frogs, and lizards.
And that's why he put them into his
revolutionary ceramics.
It's a kind of Renaissance action art.
What do you do with a plate? You put
food on it. God's bounty. And you eat
it.
And as you eat it,
the lizards,
the frogs,
the snakes begin popping up and
reminding you that earthly pleasures
[clears throat]
don't last for long. And that the devil
is always there,
always ready,
always lurking.
In the marvelous Renaissance action art
of Bernard Palissi,
something new appeared in the world.
Ceramics that pack a punch.
And the pessimism of the Renaissance
found one of its most inventive outlets.
The deeper you go in the late
Renaissance,
the weirder it gets.
Especially if you stray into Renaissance
Prague,
the unlikely Bailey wick of this
notoriously peculiar Hapsburg emperor.
Oh, okay then. This isn't really Rudolph
II. And he didn't really have an edible
chestnut for a chin or a pear for a
nose, but this is a portrait of him
painted by his remarkable court painter
Joseeppe Akimaldo.
Even in this strange stretch of
creativity that is late Renaissance art,
Arkim Baldo stands out.
The Renaissance always liked puzzles,
tricks, complexities,
but with Arkim Baldo, this taste for
conundrums
reached a startling climax.
Although he was Italian from Milan
originally, Arkim Baldo came into his
own, if that's what this can be called,
in Prague, where he found himself at the
end of the 16th century working for
Rudolph [music] II.
Plenty of people have plenty of views on
what Arkim Baldo was trying to do.
He's an alchemist, say some, a magician,
say others,
or perhaps an occultist.
It was actually simpler than all that.
He was just a man of his times. If you
poke about in the recesses of late
Renaissance art, step just a little bit
off the beaten track, you'll find lots
of signs of an appetite that had arisen
for mutation and strangeness.
Look at this thing commissioned by
Rudolph II from his favorite jeweler,
Abraham Yamnitzer.
It's the beautiful Daphne turning into a
tree made of coral
as the laws of nature are usurped by the
laws of art.
And speaking of nature, what about this
unexpected Renaissance plate at the
Asholian Museum in Oxford?
It's another disguised portrait made up
this time of interlocking penises.
That caption actually reads, "Everyone
looks at me as if I were a dickhead."
Oh, yes. The Renaissance,
rebirth of civilization.
So Arkim Baldo wasn't going against the
Renaissance grain when he began painting
these extraordinary heads. He was
continuing a Renaissance tradition. And
while he was at it, he was throwing in
some sneaky satire.
This librarian made completely of books
is having a little dig at all the showy
Renaissance book collectors who
pretended they were learned because
their shelves were heavy with unopened
books.
His
beard [music] is made out of the fur
tales that these learned Renaissance
types used as dust whisks. And the
curtain, that's the curtain that sealed
off the reading area in the great man's
private library.
Shh, it seems to say scholar at work.
There's so much clever pictorial
invention going on in Arkim Baldo.
See this plate here for instance, full
of excellent kitchen produce.
Look what happens when through the magic
of television we turn it upside down.
So Arkim Baldo was brilliant and
inventive, and you have to wonder how he
managed to get as good as he did while
working for the impossible Rudolph II.
All of the Hapsburgs were problematic.
Centuries of inbreeding had seen to
that.
But when it came to eccentricity,
Rudolph II was in a league of his own.
In art, he developed an uncontrollable
appetite for the erotic and filled his
castle walls with the paintings of
Bartame Spranganger, a sly eroticist
from Antworp, who knew exactly where to
press Rudolph's buttons.
Rudolph would arrange his pictures on
chairs so he could transport them around
the castle and look at them wherever he
wanted. And the other unusual place he
put them was up on the ceiling and he'd
lie down on the ground and look up at
his art.
And there he'd rest, gazing up at
Spranganger's Venus tempting Adonis.
A renaissance moment so naughty that
even the dog knows what's going on.
And here's his Venus in Vulcan's Forge.
I hear it gets hot in there.
Very hot.
His
other great passion apart from erotic
art was alchemy. He invited most of the
notable alchemists in Europe here to
Prague with instructions
to search for
the philosopher's stone.
>> [music]
>> This legendary substance was said to
turn lead into gold.
And it brought you what Rudolph II most
desired,
immortality.
He had his own private alchemy
laboratory where he conducted
increasingly dangerous experiments in
this desperate search
for eternal youth.
To this day, Prague enjoys a regrettable
reputation for alchemical experiment and
occult tinkering.
It's the European capital of Hocus
Pocus,
and it has Rudolph II to thank for that.
Another
of Rudolph's eccentricities was to lead
his life entirely by the horoscope. The
stars ruled his every move.
And to mark his commitment to the
cosmos,
Rudolph commissioned this painting from
the great Tinterretto in Venice.
the origin of the Milky Way.
So sure was he that the stars governed
everything,
that anyone seeking an audience with
him, be they pope or emperor,
had to have their horoscope done first.
to make sure they were suitable.
And to prove that his immortality was
written in the stars, Rudolph
commissioned his own personal horoscope
from Nostradarmus.
Unfortunately,
Nostradarmas came back with bad news.
The stars were not predicting
immortality.
So Rudolph did what any sensible, all
powerful Renaissance despot obsessed
with magic and alchemy would do.
He changed his birthday.
Having been born in the realm of cancer,
Rudolph tinkered with the cosmos and
announced that his sign was now Taurus.
But the stars weren't fooled.
Nostradamus predicted that Rudolph would
live to 73.
Unfortunately, he only made it to 60.
But in his weird Renaissance way, he
certainly left his mark.
For a brief but exciting moment, Prague
became the epicenter
of a wild wing of the Renaissance.
And to this day, the strange things done
here in the name of Rudolph II have not
been forgotten.
So perhaps he did achieve some
immortality
after all.
>> [music]
[screaming]
>> All the way through this series, I've
been arguing that the Renaissance was a
wilder epoch than we're usually told.
And to make this point, I've sometimes
had to deal with nuances.
But other times, the wildness stares you
in the face and you just can't miss it.
This is the creation of Julio Romano,
pupil of Raphael's,
who came here to Manua and produced this
preposterous chamber of the giants
in 1532.
The entire room tells the story of some
uppety giants
who are being thrown out of Mount
Olympus by Jupiter and the gods.
The Uppety giants had tried to overthrow
the divine Olympians,
but they failed.
And this is what happened to them.
So that's actually Mount Olympus up
there. And there's Jupiter, the king of
the gods, with his thunderbolts.
And on the right in the low cut tunic,
that's Juno, the queen of the gods. And
all the other gods are up there as well.
There's Apollo with his liar.
And on the other side of the mountain,
Kronos with his scythe.
Next to him with the two faces, there's
Janus.
What a fine name that is. Janus.
Now, this kind of painting is called
mannerism. At least that's what we call
it now. For centuries, it didn't really
have a name. Nobody knew what to make of
it.
Mannerism has always been a toughm to
grasp.
Its defining characteristics
don't seem to define anything sensible
or rational.
Outrageous anatomies and weird poses.
Mad colors and mysterious meanings,
peculiar storylines,
and twisty moods.
Why would Renaissance art
start doing this?
In here, for instance, to make a potty
experience even pottier, the entire
floor was originally covered in river
pebbles. And that's what you walked on.
It's as if common sense has been thrown
out of the window and everything has
grown illogical, distorted,
and strange.
And it wasn't just painting that was
affected.
It hit all the arts.
This is the famous Aenine giant by
Jambolona.
How about that for a garden ornament?
so unexpected and gargantuan
and so clearly not influenced by the
Greeks.
You get mannerist metal work as well.
Mad creations in silver and gold like
the famous salt seller made by Ben
Venuto Chelini in 1543
which lives these days in a bulletproof
[music]
box in Vienna.
He's the salt.
She's the pepper.
Everybody loves Chilini's salt cellar,
of course, with its exciting mix of
skill and surrealism,
but they don't generally love mannerism.
Purists tend to look down on it as a
decline, a sign of the Renaissance going
wrong.
But that's not how I see it. Not at all.
This is by Pontomo,
one of mannerisms acknowledged giants.
It's his visitation,
the moment in the Bible when the
pregnant Virgin Mary visits her pregnant
cousin, Elizabeth.
Elizabeth on the right is pregnant with
John the Baptist. Mary on the left is
pregnant with Jesus.
So this is a moment of momentous
sanctity, a collision of divine
pregnancies and Pontomo has imagined it
for us so unusually.
There are actually two Maryies in the
picture and two Elizabeths.
One from the front and one from the
side.
And all four of them are floating in a
frozen religious dance.
A dance in a distant dimension.
It's true of all his art.
Pontomo's eerie religious pictures
tinker with the logic in the world.
Stretch it. Recolor it.
It's as if Renaissance art has given up
on realism
and embraced the strange, the twisted,
the heightened.
These are not everyday moments.
So why should they be painted in an
everyday manner?
What we shouldn't do is see Pontomo as a
betrayer of Renaissance values or an
aberration.
All the way through this series, I've
been banging on about how the
Renaissance was never as ordered or as
stable as we've been told. It was always
full of passion, idiosyncrasy,
and darkness.
You just had to look at it the right
way.
Walk into the cyine chapel,
look up at Michelangelo
and you'll see mannerism already
happening.
The twisting figures, the opal fruit
colors,
it's all there in fledgling form.
or peer into the paintings of Leonardo
da Vinci and you'll find all the
weirdness you could ask for.
Spooky smiles, cryptic darknesses,
obscure meanings.
Mannerism wasn't a reaction. It was a
continuation.
an enlargement.
Instead of looking down on it as a
decline, we should be looking up at it
as a fabulous climax.
Do you know how many landscape painters
we've looked at so far in this series?
None.
Not a single one.
That's partly because landscape painting
was looked down on in the Renaissance,
but also because the Catholic Church
banned it at the Council of Trent, where
all profane subjects were deemed
unsuitable for art. So, you had to be a
real rebel to paint landscapes in the
Renaissance. And that's what we've got
here in Toledo. One of the fiercest
rebels ever to pick up a paintbrush.
In Spain, they called him El Greco, the
Greek.
He looks ordinary, doesn't he? But he
wasn't.
Greco was actually born in Cree, which
was a colony of Venice at the time. And
the first paintings we know by him are
by Zantine icons. So stylized and
orthodox they could have been painted in
the 10th century and not the 16th which
is when Ogreo was actually born in 1541.
At some point in his 20ies, he left Cree
and moved to Venice, where he worked
briefly in Tishon's studio,
absorbing the big colorific lessons of
Venetian art and changing his style into
something more western
with a twist of baantium in it.
By 1577,
he'd fetched up here in Toledo, which
was so far off the beaten track that the
usual Renaissance rules didn't apply.
But, and it was a big butt, there was
lots of money here. all that silver and
gold that was being shipped over from
the Americas
and which the Catholic Church was busily
spending on art.
Here in the cathedral in Toledo,
Elgreco painted a sensational disroing
of Christ.
Christ is about to be tortured and
crucified.
So the crowd is pressing in around him,
eager to strip off his clothes
and expose him fully to the pain.
I think El Greco is one of the most
exciting of all the old masters. When I
was a kid, I used to cut out pictures of
paintings from a magazine called
Knowledge and hang them on my wall.
And one of the first ones I cut out was
Elgreco's St. Martin and the Beggar. I
couldn't stop looking at it.
[music]
St. Martin, who's rich, meets a beggar
while he's [music] out riding.
The beggar is cold.
So Martin cuts his cloak in two and
shares it with him.
It's such a haunting picture with two
figures stretched out, flickering like
candles against the sky.
The Renaissance hadn't seen art like
this before.
No one had.
This is more than mannerism.
This is mannerism plus
extreme moods,
unusual colors,
wired poses.
Here in Toledo, they've recently been
commemorating the 400th anniversary of
El Greco's death in 1614.
So they cleaned up all his pictures and
we can finally see his colors as they
were meant to be seen.
Yellows that sing like canaries.
Greens so vibrant and tangy you can
taste them on your tongue. Purples
so vivid Tishon himself would have been
proud of them.
This is the hospital of St. John the
Baptist, the hospital Tava.
And that is El Greco's baptism of
Christ.
Look at all these figures who turned up
to watch, twisting, pushing, bending to
get a better look. All except God
himself,
who's sitting up there on a cloud with
his crystal ball.
So, he knows what's going to happen and
he's not celebrating.
Elgreco was so remarkable and different
that art history took 300 years to
understand him. It wasn't to the
beginning of the 20th century that he
was plucked out of obscurity and
recognized at last as a fabulously
inventive genius.
One of the pioneers of this new
understanding of El Greco was Picasso
who borrowed so much from his distant
master.
There's a painting in New York at the
Met called the opening of the fifth seal
and it shows that moment in St. John's
revelations when the fifth seal is
opened just before the end of the world
and the Christian martyrs call up to God
to avenge them for their tortures.
And up in the sky the heavens crack open
as if someone has thrown a brick at
them.
The opening of the fifth seal used to
hang around the corner from Picasso in
Paris and it inspired his most famous
painting, the Demoiselle Davinong. The
picture that started cubism.
Fractured planes,
thrusting bodies.
Elgreco's spiky disruption
was such an inspirational gift to the
future.
What I've tried to do in this series is
challenge the idea that the Renaissance
was neat and ordered, that the knowledge
of the ancients was rediscovered and the
civilization of the Greeks reborn.
A bit of that went on, but most of the
time in most corners of the Renaissance,
art wasn't pursuing knowledge or
remembering the Greeks. It was doing
what art always does.
Imagining the unimaginable
and inventing things,
expressing its emotions
and describing its fears,
enjoying itself,
and breaking the rules.
So if anyone tells you the Renaissance
was a period of civilized calm,
go out there and argue with them.